<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ordinance impowring the commissioners of the customes, and others, for the better suppressing of drunkennes and prophane cursing and swearing, in persons imployed under them.</title>
            <title>Orders in Council. 1654-06-30.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Lord Protector (1653-1658 : O. Cromwell)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74544</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1064_25</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210262</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869076</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869076</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169225</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74544)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169225)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 159:E1064[25])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ordinance impowring the commissioners of the customes, and others, for the better suppressing of drunkennes and prophane cursing and swearing, in persons imployed under them.</title>
                  <title>Orders in Council. 1654-06-30.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Lord Protector (1653-1658 : O. Cromwell)</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Council of State. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>457-459, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf bears an order to print dated: 30 June, 1654.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Swearing --  Great Britain --  Law and legislation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Social life and customs --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="457" facs="tcp:169225:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>seal of the commonwealth of England</figDesc>
               </figure> AN ORDINANCE Impowring the COMMISSIONERS OF THE CUSTOMES, And others, for the better ſuppreſsing of DRUNKENNES and prophane CUR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SING and SWEARING, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons imployed under them.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas ſeveral perſons, as Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Porters, Water-men, and others, who are imployed upon the Keys, as alſo upon the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of Thames, in Ships, Boats, and Lighters, and in Thames-ſtreet, and other Streets and Lanes adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent within the City of <hi>London,</hi> for ſhipping and unſhipping, packing, carrying, craning, and removing goods and Merchandize, and
<pb n="458" facs="tcp:169225:2"/> other affairs in matters relating thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, are very ordinarily Drunk, and do alſo prophane and blaſpheme the holy name of God by Curſing and Swearing, to the great diſhonor of God, the ſcandal of the Profeſſors and profeſſion of the Goſpel among us, and of the preſent Government; For the preventing whereof, Bee it Ordein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by His Highneſs the Lord Protector, by and with the conſent of His Council, That the Commiſſioners for the Cuſtomes for the time being, bee, and are hereby au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized and required to take care that the Laws of this Nation againſt Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Swearing and Curſing bee put in execution, againſt all ſuch perſons as ſhall bee guilty of the crimes aforeſaid; And for that purpoſe ſhall, and hereby have the power and authoritie of Iuſtices of the Peace within the ſaid places. And every Officer and Officers, Deputie and Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Commiſſioners of the Cuſtomes, having a Commiſſion whereby they are De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted and authorized to bee Officers and Deputies under the hand and Seals of the ſaid Commiſſioners, ſhall have, and hereby have power, and are authorized to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend and attache, and in ſafe cuſtody to bring before the ſaid Commiſſioners, or any one of them ſitting at the Cuſtom-houſ <hi>London,</hi> every perſon or perſons whom they ſhall ſee to bee Drunk, or ſhall hear to Swear, Curſ, and blaſpheme the holy name of God, as is aforeſaid, and ſhall have power, and hereby have power, to execute any power or powers, authoritie or authorities in this caſe, which
<pb n="459" facs="tcp:169225:2"/> by Law, any Conſtable may or ought to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe or uſe, although the ſaid Officer or Officers have no particular Warrant of the Commiſſioners, aforeſaid, for apprehending any the offenders for the offences aforeſaid, as in the like caſes are uſually iſſued unto ſworn Conſtables, by Iuſtices of the Peace upon the like occaſions; and all perſon and perſons whom any of the ſaid Officer and Officers ſhall require to bee aiding and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting unto them, in the apprehending and bringing before the ſaid Commiſſioners any ſuch offenders, are hereby required to bee aiding and aſſiſting unto them therein accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly: And in caſe of refuſal, ſuch puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and proceedings ſhall bee had and awarded againſt them, as by Law may bee and ought to be upon every perſon that ſhall refuſe to bee aiding and aſſiſting unto any ſworn Conſtable or Conſtables, when requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thereunto.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <head>
               <hi>Friday</hi> 30 <hi>June,</hi> 1654.</head>
            <p>ORdered by His Highneſs the <hi>Lord PROTECTOR</hi> and the Council, That this Ordinance bee forthwith Printed and Publiſhed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen. Scobel, <hi>Clerk of the Council.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
